A Guide to the George F. Keesee Collection
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
The George F. Keesee Collection 1869-1924
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
86/Sep/17
1.7 linear feet. 29 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Mrs. Edgar J. Fisher Jr.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. George Fisk Keesee as born on 05 September, 1842 in Richmond, Virginia. Orphaned at an early age, Keesee was raised by his father's friend, and prominent businessman, Cornelius Crowe.
At age 19, he joined the Confederate army. As a member of the Virginia Life Guards, he participated in what would become the first engagement of the war, the Battle of Bethel. (10 Jun, 1861) Keesee's war career was short lived, as he became ill and was reassigned to the defense of Richmond, a task he continued until war's end.
He decided on a career in dentistry, and graduated Valedictorian of the Baltimore College of Dental Surgery in 1869. Keesee set up his practice in Richmond where he remained active until his retirement in 1924. Keesee was a founding member of the Virginia Dental Association and was named Secretary, a post he would hold for over 50 years. He also helped organize the Richmond Dental Society serving the organization in a variety of capacities. At the time of his death, he was an honorary lifetime member and president emeritus.
Keesee received many accolades during his long career including being named Secretary-General of the 1907 Jamestown Exposition National Dental Conference. Keesee was reelected as secretary of the Richmond Randolph Masonic Lodge a record 59 consecutive times. He also served as its Worshipful Master from 1875-1877. His portrait still hangs in his Masonic Lodge grand hall.
Keesee married the former Sallie Bennett on 30 November, 1871 and they had five children. Keesee died 09 October, 1924 in Richmond. He is buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Scope and Content
The core of this collection is Keesee's dental office ledgers which are complete for the years of his practice. (1869-1924). There is also a collection of speeches written by Keesee, as well as some memorabilia. The collection does not include any materials documenting Keesee's work with the Masons, or the dental associations in which he belonged.
Arrangement
This collection is compiled by merging accessioning numbers: 86/Sep/17, 88/Sep/18, 89/Mar/06, 90/Jul/19.
Contents List
- Dental Office Ledgers (Box-folder 1)
  a typicial entry would include the work done, a price, any payment made. There will be an occasional change in address.
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1869-1872 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1873-1876 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1877-1879 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1880-1884 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1885-1888 (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1889-1892 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1892-1894 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1895-1897 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1898-1900 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1901-1903 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1904-1906 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1907-1910 (Box-folder 1.12)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1911-1914 (Box-folder 1.13)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1915-1918 (Box-folder 1.14)
  - Dental Office Ledgers 1919-1924 (Box-folder 1.15)
- Papers and personal effects. (Box-folder 2)
  - Papers written by Keesee. (Box-folder 2.1)
    - Valedictorian address, Baltimore College of Dental Surgery. 1869 (Box-folder 2.1)
    - Handwritten address, "History of Dentistry" in Virginia., Handwritten in pencil, with envelope. (Box-folder 2.1)
    - Handwritten reply to telegram sent by Dr. Harry Bear, then Secretary of the Virginia Dental Association., Handwritten in pencil (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Biographies of Keesee. (Box-folder 2.2)
    This folder contains several biographies of Keesee.
    - Biography written by Dr. Burton Lee Thorpe for the 1907 Jamestown Exposition National Dental Conference. 1907 (Box-folder 2.2)
    - Biography written by Dr. Harry Bear, Dean, School of Dentistry, MCV. 1925 (Box-folder 2.2)
    - Biography written by Keesee's son, George H. Keesee (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Photograph Collection, Photograph (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Memorabilia (Box-folder 2.4)
    This folder contains medals, a name plate, and several appointment books.
    - Medal 1907 (Box-folder 2.4)
      Member, 1907 Jamestown Exposition National Dental Award
    - Medal 1915 (Box-folder 2.4)
      25th reunion of the United Civil War Veterans.
    - Brass Doorplate (Box-folder 2.4)
      Dr. Keesee
    - Appointment books 1910, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 2.4)
    - Bylaws booklet 1917 (Box-folder 2.4)
      Virginia Dental Association.
    - Bylaws 1916 (Box-folder 2.4)
      Richmond Dental Association.
    - Program 1919 (Box-folder 2.4)
      Richmond Dental Society meeting